Welcome to Chapter 5, Red Blood Cell Disorders.
The vast majority of this chapter actually deals with anemias.
We're going to subdivide the anemias and talk about them in groups.
However, before we actually begin, it's important to gain a general understanding of anemia.
Anemia is defined as a reduction in circulating red blood cell mass.
This is the technical definition of anemia,
and we're well aware of the fact that red blood cells carry the vast majority of oxygen
within the blood, in particular the hemoglobin within the red blood cell,
carries the vast majority of oxygen within the blood.
And therefore, if patients have a reduction in red blood cell mass,
they're going to present with signs and symptoms of hypoxia.
Some of those signs would include weakness, fatigue, and dyspnea,
dyspnea being shortness of breath, pale conjunctiva in skin,
and this is a relatively good clinical test.
Pale conjunctiva is a good sign that there is an anemia.
The patient may present with headache and lightheadedness due to hypoxia
to the central nervous system, in particular the brain.
And the patient may even exhibit signs and symptoms of angina.
Angina is chest pain, and because there's low oxygen in the blood,
there would be low oxygen delivery to the heart.
And if the patient has some preexisting situation that has already decreased
the blood flow to the heart, for example, coronary artery disease,
then a further decrease in oxygen in the little bit of blood that's actually going to the heart
could actually result in signs and symptoms of angina.
These are the classic signs and symptoms of hypoxia.
Now, once we have a patient with signs and symptoms of hypoxia,
then the next discussion becomes how we can prove that they actually have an anemia.
And remember that the technical definition of an anemia is a decrease in red blood cell mass.
Unfortunately, it's very difficult to measure the red blood cell mass.
Obviously, we can't take a patient and bleed them and then measure how much their red blood cells weigh.
So it's very difficult to measure.
There are ways to do it, but it would be very expensive and very difficult.
So instead of measuring red blood cell mass, we use some surrogate markers.
And these surrogate markers help us to determine or make an effort to determine
exactly what the patient's red blood cell mass might be.
The three key laboratory studies that are used are hemoglobin, hematocrit, and the red blood cell count.
So these three markers, hemoglobin, hematocrit, and the red blood cell count,
are used as surrogates for red blood cell mass.
Now, you could actually stop me and say, well, you know, why are these surrogates,
why don't we just say that they equal the red blood cell mass?
And the answer is that each of these is concentration dependent.
And so they could, in some circumstances, not be a good estimate of red blood cell mass.
For example, a woman may have normal red blood cell mass when she's pregnant.
However, because her blood volume increases so much, her hemoglobin and hematocrit actually go down.
And because the hemoglobin and hematocrit go down,
that doesn't mean that she's got a decrease in red blood cell mass.
It just simply means that she's got more blood volume, and so she's diluted out her normal red blood cell mass.
So that might be one circumstance in which a patient could have a lower hemoglobin or hematocrit,
but would still have a normal red blood cell mass.
Another example, just to, again, highlight this principle, let's say a patient gets a gunshot wound.
If they get a gunshot wound, they're obviously going to bleed out both red blood cells and fluid.
And so immediately after the gunshot wound, when there's blood loss,
the patient's hemoglobin and hematocrit would be normal.
What's going to show you that there was actually blood loss is that when you give the patient fluid,
or when the patient eventually gets fluid back into their system,
that's going to dilute down the remaining red blood cells,
and then that will result in a decrease in the hemoglobin and hematocrit.
And so, again, another reason why these are just surrogates.
But for our discussions and for the purposes of what we want to consider,
I think that the hemoglobin and hematocrit and the red blood cell count
are relatively useful for determining red blood cell mass.
The technical definition of anemia is a hemoglobin less than 3.5 grams in males
and a hemoglobin or a hemoglobin less than 12.5 grams in females.
We accept a lower hemoglobin in females because females normally lose a little bit of blood
during their menstrual cycle, and therefore their hemoglobin may be slightly lower in the normal female.
When you think about anemias, there's a lot of ways to divide anemias.
And I think this, for me, at least as a student, had made anemia a particularly difficult subject.
For example, you could look at some textbooks, and some textbooks will say,
divide anemias based on underproduction or overdestruction.
And that would be one way to look at anemias.
Another textbook might look at anemias and say,
well, let's divide anemias based on problems with the red blood cell
and problems with something other than the red blood cell,
so extrinsic or intrinsic defects.
That's another way to look at anemia.
However, my personal feeling is that the best way for a student
who's learning about anemia to understand anemia
is to divide it based on the MCV.
The MCV is the mean corpuscular volume,
and it tells you basically, it gives you an estimate of the size of the red blood cell.
And for me, if you understand anemia based on the size of the red blood cell,
that makes it very easy to learn the different anemias.
And you'll see why as I take you through the remainder of this lecture.
But I'm fairly confident that once you learn anemias the way that I'm going to explain it to you,
you'll actually be very comfortable with anemias, you'll be very comfortable with them clinically,
you'll be very comfortable with them for examination purposes.
And of course, anemias are something that we regularly and routinely see both clinically
as well as on any type of examination.
Let's just remind ourselves that the normal red blood cell has an MCV,
or a mean corpuscular volume, of about 80 to 100.
That's the normal.
80 to 100 would be normal.
Less than 80 is considered microcytic, i.e. the cells are smaller than they normally should be,
and greater than 100 is considered macrocytic, i.e. the cells are bigger than they normally should be.
And so we're going to divide anemia into three types,
microcytic anemias, macrocytic anemias, and normocytic anemias.
And so these are the next three sections that you're going to cover,
and we'll do them, obviously, we'll take them one at a time and do them sequentially.
So let's stop there.
That's the basic introduction, and the next section is going to deal with microcytic anemias.